Okay, next section, benign tumors and fibrocystic changes.
We're going to start with fibrocystic change,
and in order to understand this,
I'm going to take you back to the whiteboard.
So let's remind ourselves that the functional unit of the breast
is called the terminal duct lobular unit,
so that you've got this terminal duct,
which feeds into something called the lobule,
and of course the lobule contains these small little glands
which produce milk.
So that's the terminal duct lobular unit.
Now the idea in fibrocystic change
is that you get cystic change of these circles,
so that they become bigger.
That's what we mean by cysts.
You can also get cystic change here of the terminal duct.
And at the same time, as you get those cysts,
that's going to stretch the connective tissue a little bit,
and so you're going to get a little bit of fibrosis
in between the connective tissue,
and hence the term fibrocystic change.
Now this is the most common change in a premenopausal woman,
and of course I call it a change
because we currently believe it to be hormone-mediated,
and it's basically a normal variation
that can occur within breast tissue
as a consequence of the up and down levels
of estrogen and progesterone
that are, again, present within the blood.
So you've got this rising and changing levels
of estrogen and progesterone over time
that can result in fibrocystic change.
The classic presentation on physical exam
would be to have a vague irregularity
to the breast tissue
where you don't feel a definite mass,
but it feels a little lumpy in places,
and so they also call that the lumpy breast.
Usually it's in the upper outer quadrant,
but that's nothing special
because we know that much of the breast parenchyma
in a female is in the upper outer quadrant.
That's the highest density of breast tissue
in the female breast anatomically,
and when you look at the tissue on gross exam,
you can actually see the cysts,
and when you see the cysts,
they often have a blue color to them,
so we call them blue-dome cysts on gross exam.
All of this is stated in your text.
I'll just quickly run through it with you.
Development of fibrosis in cysts,
most common change in premenopausal breast,
lumpy breast, upper outer quadrant,
and the cysts usually have a blue-domed appearance
on gross exam.
I've explained all of that using the whiteboard already.
Now, important to note that fibrocystic change is benign.
Number one, inherently, in and of itself, it's benign,
and number two, it carries no increased risk for cancer.
So the classic fibrocystic change carries no increased risk for cancer.
However, sometimes when a patient has fibrocystic change
and you do a biopsy to confirm it,
you can find other features,
and some of those associated other features
do carry a risk for cancer in the future.
And so that's what I want to briefly mention here,
and this is particularly high yield,
so I'm going to run through just the few ones
that classically show up on examinations.
One possibility is that when a woman has fibrocystic change,
and she's simply got fibrosis, and she's got cysts,
and some of those cysts can be lined by apocrine metoplasia.
Now, important to note that when you have fibrosis, cysts,
and apocrine metoplasia, or any one of these three,
they are benign, and there's no increased risk
for future development of invasive carcinoma.
So that's the first set, fibrosis, cysts, and apocrine metoplasia.
Now, this apocrine metoplasia is actually particularly high yield
because one of the general principles in pathology
is that any time you have metoplasia,
it's usually a risk factor for the future development of cancer.
For example, Barrett's esophagus is a non-ciliated columnar cell
with goblet cell metoplasia
that increases the risk for development of adenocarcinoma.
For example, squamous metoplasia in the lung
increases the risk for dysplasia
and the subsequent development of squamous cell carcinoma in smokers.
However, apocrine metoplasia, very high yield to note,
apocrine metoplasia does not increase the risk for cancer.
This is why I'm emphasizing it so much
because despite the fact that we call it a metaplasia,
there's no increased risk for cancer.
Okay, the second change that you could see
is something called ductal hyperplasia,
and the idea here is that you've got your duct, correct,
that goes in, and it goes into the terminal duct lobular unit,
so this would be the lobule.
And remember that the normal lining of the duct is two layers.
You've got an epithelial layer, which is like a columnar cell,
and underneath that you've got a myoepithelial cell.
Now, normally there should only be two cells
that line this entire surface.
However, you can have hyperplasia
where you get excess numbers of cells
and where you get excess numbers of cells
and those cells are benign.
We call that ductal hyperplasia.
Now, ductal hyperplasia has a two times increased risk
of development of cancer,
so that if a normal woman has her standard risk,
she now, if she has ductal hyperplasia on a biopsy,
she now has a two times increased risk
of developing invasive carcinoma sometime in the future.
Another disorder that could result in an increased risk
would be something called sclerosing adenosis.
Examiners do ask about this, so I'm going to discuss it.
The idea here is if you've got the normal terminal duct lobular unit,
remember that normally, let's say that in this normal unit,
you should have had three or four glands.
Now, in adenosis, what happens is you have too many glands,
so instead of having three or four,
you have, I don't know, 10 or 15, for example.
That would be adenosis.
And then sometimes you can get some fibrosis
associated with that adenosis,
making this area quote-unquote hard
or with deposition of collagen,
and that's called sclerosis.
And so sclerosing adenosis, where it to be present,
increases the risk by twofold,
so that the patients who have sclerosing adenosis on a biopsy
will have a two-times-increased risk
for the future development of invasive carcinoma.
Now, very important to note, and high yield for examination,
is that sclerosing adenosis is classically often calcified,
so that there can be calcifications
associated with sclerosing adenosis,
and that may be why the biopsy occurs.
A woman goes for a mammogram,
there's increased calcifications,
and so a biopsy is performed,
and it actually turns out to be sclerosing adenosis.
Again, sclerosing adenosis is benign in and of itself,
but it pretends an increased risk for the development,
for the future development of breast cancer.
And the third possibility that I've listed here
is atypical hyperplasia.
Now, it's possible when you look at the terminal duct
and the lobule, it's possible that you could have
atypical cells that are increased within the duct,
or you could have atypical cells
that are increased within the lobule.
When it's in the duct,
we call that atypical ductal hyperplasia.
When it's in the lobule,
we call that atypical lobular hyperplasia.
Classically, I'm simplifying this a little bit,
but that's the classic understanding.
But the point is that if you have
any type of atypical hyperplasia on a biopsy,
the woman now has a five times increased risk
for the future development of invasive carcinoma.
Now, I'd like to say one more thing
that shows up on examinations,
and that is that you have to know, first of all,
that the increased risk is an increased risk
for invasive carcinoma, all right?
That's important.
It's an increased risk for invasive carcinoma,
and that that increased risk applies to both breasts,
so that the risk is for cancer in either breast.
So if the biopsy was performed on the right breast
and they saw atypical hyperplasia on the right breast,
the risk for cancer applies to both the right
and the left breast,
so that's important to understand as well.
Here's a classic picture of apocrine metaplasia.
All I'm trying to show you is that these cells
have abundant pink cytoplasm,
and they're slightly larger than the normal cells.
Again, most important take-home point
is that for you to know that apocrine metaplasia
has no increased risk for breast cancer,
despite the fact that it's called metaplasia.
Now, introductal papilloma is the next type of disorder
that we want to discuss, and this is a benign tumor.
Notice that it's an oma.
It's a true mass.
In introductal papilloma,
the way you want to think about this
is to simply go back to normal.
Let's talk about the very large duct
that goes out into the skin of the nipple.
Now, when you have a large duct
within the anterior portion of the breast,
one of the possibilities that can occur
is that within this large duct,
which, of course, is normally lined
with just two layers of cells,
you can develop a finger-like projection
which is lined by epithelial cells.
All right?
And, of course, a growth of a finger-like projection
lined by epithelial cells would be a papillary lesion,
papillary because it has a finger-like projection
with a fibrovascular core blood vessel
running through the center.
So that would be a papillary lesion,
and when you have a papillary lesion,
one of the key features of the papillary lesion
is that it often bleeds,
producing a bloody nipple discharge.
So the classic association with a papillary lesion
is a bloody nipple discharge.
Now, for the most part,
these papillary lesions,
especially in a premenopausal woman,
are going to represent papilloma.
Something called intraductal papilloma.
Intraductal because it's in the duct
and papilloma because it's benign.
And one of the very important hallmarks
concerning the intraductal papilloma
is that since this is a benign proliferation
of epithelium,
you'll actually have two cell types
lining this intraductal papilloma.
You'll have your standard epithelial cell,
and underneath that,
you'll have a myoepithelial cell.
So this is a very high yield,
shows up in exams all the time,
principle,
that when you have an intraductal papilloma,
there will be the standard two cell layers.
There will be an epithelial cell,
underneath which is a myoepithelial cell.
Another important thing about intraductal papilloma,
it usually occurs in a premenopausal woman.
Now, it is possible to develop a papillary growth
just like this.
However, instead of it being an intraductal papilloma,
it's a papillary carcinoma.
That's a possibility as well.
Now, how would you distinguish the two?
Well, number one,
a papillary carcinoma is more common as women age,
and it's more classically seen in a postmenopausal woman.
So, the older a woman gets,
the more likely she is to develop a papillary carcinoma
as opposed to an intraductal papilloma.
That'd be one.
But more importantly,
the key distinction is made
by the lack of these myoepithelial cells,
so that you wouldn't see these myoepithelial cells.
They would be absent in a papillary carcinoma,
and that is classically very high yield
for examination purposes.
They love to go after this
because it's an opportunity
to go after normal histology, in effect.
So, that's the discussion of papilloma.
Now, let's read together.
So, I say,
intraductal papilloma.
This is a papillary growth,
large duct.
It has fibrovascular projections
lined by epithelial cells
and myoepithelial cells, right?
So, we're talking about the benign variant,
the intraductal papilloma.
It's going to present with bloody nipple discharge
in a premenopausal woman,
but you must always have in the back of your mind
papillary carcinoma.
Again, the two features of papillary carcinoma
would be a lack of myoepithelial cells,
so you wouldn't have that second layer
of myoepithelial cells, number one.
And number two,
it's much more likely as women age,
so that this would classically be a
postmenopausal female
with bloody nipple discharge.
And, of course, papillary lesions,
the hallmark is bloody nipple discharge.
The next disorder is called fibroadenoma.
Fibro means fibrous tissue,
and adeno means glands,
and oma means you've got a true tumor.
So, this is a tumor of fibrous tissue and glands.
It is the most common benign tumor of the breast.
Most common benign tumor of the breast.
Now, it's classically seen in a premenopausal woman.
In fact, you could say it's the most common tumor
in premenopausal females.
I'm going to repeat that.
Most common tumor in premenopausal females.
Now, this grows as a well-circumscribed,
mobile, marble-like mass.
These are the classic descriptions of a benign tumor
from our neoplasia chapter.
Remember, I told you that when you have a benign tumor,
it tends to be very distinct from the rest of the tissue,
i.e., well-circumscribed.
It tends to be mobile,
indicating that it hasn't invaded into, for example,
the chest wall or the rest of the breast tissue.
And it's marble-like,
and that's, again, indicating that it's clearly distinct
from the rest of the breast.
And so these are some classic clinical features
of a fibroadenoma.
These tumors are estrogen-sensitive,
and that's important.
For example, they grow during pregnancy.
They can be painful during the menstrual cycle.
They can shrink in size
when a woman undergoes menopause.
And so this is an important feature of fibroadenoma.
And the most important, benign.
But that's obvious because of the name.
It's an adenoma.
It's not an adenocarcinoma, right?
And then number two,
no increased risk for cancer.
Once a woman has a fibroadenoma,
she's going to ask you,
so does this mean I have cancer?
No, you don't.
Does this mean I have an increased risk to get cancer?
So it is benign with no increased risk for carcinoma.
Here's a classic picture of a fibroadenoma.
What I'm trying to highlight here,
this is the normal.
This is the tumor.
You can see that the tumor contains this fibrous tissue,
which, let's label this with F.
And then you can see that it also contains these glands as well.
And so this is the combination of fibroadenoma,
because it's a mass.
Now notice that this is sharply demarcated from the adjacent breast tissue.
Again, it's a well-circumscribed, mobile-like,
very distinct mass within the breast.
There is another type of fibroadenoma-like tumor
that can develop within the breast.
It's called a phloides tumor.
It's very similar to the fibroadenoma
in the sense that it has fibrous tissue and glands,
but there's an overgrowth of the fibrous component, high yield.
There is an overgrowth of the fibrous component.
Now that overgrowth of the fibrous component
then pushes out the tumor into these leaf-like projections.
And this is what it looks like.
So you've got this overgrowth of the fibrous component here.
I'm labeling it with an F.
And as you get the overgrowth,
it pushes out the surface,
creating these leaf-like projections.
So I'm circling this leaf-like projection.
And that's the classic image of a phloides tumor.
Now I'd like to go back and remind you
that when you have a fibroadenoma,
that's usually a premenopausal woman.
However, a phloides tumor is more commonly seen
in postmenopausal women,
so women that are a little bit older
than that of a fibroadenoma category.
And another important thing about the phloides tumor
is that it can be malignant.
But that would go along with the idea
of it arising in postmenopausal women
because we know that cancer is much more common
in a postmenopausal woman.
It's really classically a disease of postmenopausal women
with one exception,
and that would be genetic breast cancer,
which we're going to talk about at the very end.
So again, that's the picture of fibroadenoma.
And that closes off our discussion on the benign lesions.
And then we're now going to enter
into a discussion of breast cancer.